Guide to the Walt Whitman Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Adrian Van Sinderen Gift, 1842-1925; Series V; 3.13; (8 boxes)
  - WRITINGS
    - Autobiographical Writings
      - ["The newspapers still keep up..."] holograph manuscript, corrected, [1871?] (Box 3, Folder 123)
      - "A Poet's 68th Year," holograph manuscript, corrected, [1887] (Box 3, Folder 124)
      - "The Van Velsors," holograph manuscript and clipping, corrected (Box 3, Folder 125)
      - ["Walt Whitman, from Holland..."], holograph manuscript, corrected, 1890 May (Box 3, Folder 126)
      - ["Walt Whitman who has been away..."], holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 127)
    - Diaries
      - "Feb. 9 [18]80," holograph manuscript, signed, 1880 Feb 9 (Box 3, Folder 128)
    - Lectures and Speeches
      - "At the Complimentary Dinner, Camden, New Jersey, May 31, 1889," galley proofs, corrected (3 copies), [ca. 1889 May] (Box 3, Folder 129)
      - ["How often since that dark and chilly Saturday..."], drafts, holograph, corrected, [1880] (Box 3, Folder 130)
    - Notes and Notebooks
      - "Adieu for the Present," holograph fragment, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 131)
      - "As I Sit Writing Here," holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 132)
        Includes letter to Whitman, dated May 4, 1888, from The Herald
      - "The Idea of Reconciliation," holograph fragment, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 133)
      - "The Man-of-War Bird," holograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 134)
      - "A Night Battle in the Late War," holograph fragment, corrected, 1863 May 2 (Box 3, Folder 135)
      - "Old Mr. and Mrs. M," holograph manuscript, 1877 Aug 24 (Box 3, Folder 136)
      - "Pictures," holograph notebook, corrected, [ca. 1850] (Box 3, Folder 137)
      - "Putrid Politics," holograph fragment, corrected, [ca. 1873] (Box 3, Folder 138)
        Includes letter, dated Dec. 29, [18]73, to A. R. Butts
      - "Written Impromptu in an Album," holograph manuscript, part of "Small Memoranda," November Boughs, 1883 Dec 26 (Box 3, Folder 139)
      - Untitled holograph manuscripts and fragments, [1882?]-88, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 140)
      - Untitled holograph notebook, 1876, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 141)
        Conditions Governing Access
        Restricted fragile material. Digital reference surrogate is available. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
      - Untitled holograph notebook, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 142)
    - Outlines and Proposals
      - "Memoranda for a Year (1863)"
        - Holograph manuscript, corrected, [1863 Oct 21?] (Box 3, Folder 143)
        - Typescript carbon, corrected, [1863 Oct 21?] (Box 3, Folder 144)
    - Poetry
      - "As in a Swoon"
        - Holograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 145)
      - Complete Poems & Prose of Walt Whitman, 1855-1888
        - Holograph notes, corrected, 1888 (Box 3, Folder 146)
          Includes clipping
      - Drum Taps
        - Manuscript poster, [ca. 1865] (Box 3, Folder 147)
      - "Fancies at Navesink"
        - Galley proof and holograph drafts, corrected and bound
          Includes engraving by S.[amuel] Hollyer
      - "For Queen Victoria's Birthday"
        - Galley proof, corrected and signed (Box 3, Folder 148)
      - "Funeral Interpolations"
        - Holograph manuscript, corrected and signed, [1888] (Box 3, Folder 149)
      - "Going Somewhere"
        - Galley proof, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 150)
      - ["I cross'd the Nevadas..."]
        - Holograph fragment, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 151)
      - "Italian Music in Dakota"
        - Holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 152)
        - Galley proof, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 153)
      - Leaves of Grass (4th edition)
        - "Inscription," holograph, [ca. 1867?] (Box 3, Folder 154)
      - Leaves of Grass (1881-82 edition)
        - Page proofs of contents (2 copies), with notes in Whitman's hand, [1881] (Box 3, Folder 155)
      - "My 71st Year"
        - Galley proof, corrected, 1889 Nov (Box 3, Folder 156)
      - "Old Age's Ship & Crafty Death's"
        - Galley proof, corrected (Box 3, Folder 157)
      - "Osceola", n.d.
        Holograph manuscript, corrected
      - "Rise, Lurid Stars"
        - Draft, photostat, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 158)
        - Holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 159)
        - Printed version, Century Magazine, [1911 Feb] (Box 3, Folder 160)
      - "Song of the Universal"
        - Holograph drafts, corrected, and printed version, bound, 1874, n.d.
          Includes etching by T. Johnson
      - "Thou Who Hast Slept All Night Upon the Storm"
        - [Page proof?], n.d. (Box 3, Folder 161)
      - "To Get the Final Lilt of Songs"
        - Galley proof, inscribed, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 162)
      - "To the Sun-Set Breeze"
        - Galley proof, 1889 (Box 3, Folder 163)
      - "To the Year 1889"
        - Holograph manuscript, corrected and signed (Box 3, Folder 164)
        - Galley proof, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 165)
      - "The Unexpressed"
        - Holograph manuscript, corrected and signed (Box 3, Folder 166)
      - "A Voice From Death"
        - Holograph manuscript, corrected and bound
          Includes portrait by E. Whittlesey Kotz
      - "Walt Whitman's Last Good-Bye My Fancy"
        - Preface, holograph manuscript, corrected and signed, [ca. 1891] (Box 3, Folder 167)
      - ["What the word of power unbroken?"]
        - Holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 168)
      - [While behind all firm and erect as ever..."]
        - Holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 169)
      - "With Husky-Haughty Lips, O Sea!"
        - Drafts, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 170)
        - Galley proof, corrected (2 copies), n.d. (Box 3, Folder 171)
        - Galley proof, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 172)
        - Printed version, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 173)
    - Writings of Others
      Ingersoll, Robert Green
      - "Address at the Funeral of Walt Whitman," galley proof, [1892]
      - "Testimonial to Walt Whitman," page proofs, [1890] (Box 3, Folder 174)
  - PHOTOGRAPHS
    - Walt Whitman
      - Brady National Photographic Art Gallery (Washington, D.C.), 1865-73, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 175)
      - "Edy Bros.", 1880 Sep 22 (Box 4, Folder 176)
      - [G. F. E. Pearsall?], [1873] (Box 4, Folder 177)
      - George C. Cox, 1887, n.d.
      - Gurney & Son, 1871 (Box 4, Folder 178)
      - [Gutekunst, Frederick (1852-1907)?], 1873, 1888 (Box 4, Folder 179)
      - Major & Knapp Engraving, Manufacturing & Lithographic Co., 1879-85, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 180)
      - Sarony & Co.
        See: Major & Knapp Engraving, Manufacturing & Lithographic Co., Box 4, folder 180
      - Kurtz, W[illiam?], 1879 May (Box 4, Folder 181)
        With Harry and Kitty [Johnston]
      - W. Shaw Warren, 1875 (Box 4, Folder 182)
      - Unidentified, 1864-85, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 183)
        Includes tintype of Whitman in buggy with unidentified man
    - Other People
      - Traubel, Horace and Laurens Maynard, 1895 Feb 17 (Box 4, Folder 184)
        Photograph by Laurens Maynard
      - Whitman's funeral, 1892
        Photographs by John C. Hemment
  - ARTWORK AND OBJECTS
    - L. [Dolice?] woodcut, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 185)
      See also: Other Papers, Box 4, folder 206
    - [Alex?] Finta bronze medallion, 1925 (Box Art, Folder 186)
    - [Herbert Gilchrist] etching, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 187)
    - S.[amuel] Hollyer engravings, 1855, 1888 (Box 4, Folder 188)
      See also: Writings, Poetry, "Fancies at Navesink"
    - T. Johnson etching
      See: Writings, Poetry, "Song of the Universal"
    - J. Jusko bronze medallion, n.d. (Box Art, Folder 189)
    - E. Whittlesey Kotz portrait
      See: Writings, Poetry, "A Voice From Death"
    - G[ustav?] Kruell woodcut, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 190)
    - R. Tait Mackenzie bronze medallion, [1919?] (Box Art, Folder 191)
    - Samuel Murray bust, 1892 (Box Art, Folder 192)
    - George W. Waters oil painting, 1877 (Box Art, Folder 193)
    - Bertrand Zadig woodcut
    - Unidentified, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 194)
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - Address in Whitman's hand, 1879 (Box 4, Folder 195)
    - Cancelled check, 1877 May 16 (Box 4, Folder 196)
    - Certificate of copyright for Leaves of Grass, 1872 Jul 13 (Box 4, Folder 197)
    - Confederate bill, 1864 Feb 17 (Box 4, Folder 198)
    - Eyeglasses, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 199)
      Includes note from Mary O. Davis, dated March 26, 1895, to J. H. Johnston
    - "The Fair Pilot of Loch Uribol," story, printed version, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 200)
      Includes note and envelope with inscription in Whitman's hand
    - [Gold?] coin, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 201)
      Includes inscription "Walt Whitman to Mary Davis. Xmas 1891"
    - Postcard, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 202)
    - Prescription signed by R[ichard] M[aurice] Bucke, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 203)
      Includes envelope with inscription in Whitman's hand
    - Printed ephemera, [1880], n.d. (Box 4, Folder 204)
    - Receipt in Whitman's hand, 1886 Nov 5 (Box 4, Folder 205)
    - Woodcut block, n.d. (Box Art, Folder 206)
  - CASES (Box 5–9)
    There are 57 cases accompanying the Van Sinderen manuscript material. Manuscripts and letters were removed and the cases stored separately.
- Material from Other Sources, 1866-1949; Series VI; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Acquired by gift or purchase from various sources. Sources indicated on individual folders.
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Letters from Walt Whitman
      - Bellows, Edward D., 1877 Nov 29 (Box 10, Folder 207)
      - George Routledge and Sons, 1868 Feb 19 (Box 10, Folder 208)
      - Linton, [W. J. (William James)?], 1877 Jan 23 (Box 10, Folder 209)
      - Oldach, ----, 1890 Oct 21 (Box 10, Folder 210)
        Letter addressed to David McKay
      - Speed, [James?], 1866 Oct 13 (Box 10, Folder 211)
        Photostat of letter from Whitman
      - Unidentified, 1879 Apr 13 (Box 10, Folder 212)
      - Empty envelopes, 1886 Nov 23 (Box 10, Folder 213)
    - Letters to Walt Whitman
      - Knortz, Karl, 1883 Sep 14 (Box 10, Folder 214)
        Includes enclosures with note in Whitman's hand
      - Price, A[bby] H., n.d. (Box 10, Folder 215)
    - Third-Party Correspondence
      - Freeman, Maurice to "Mr. Goldsmith", 1927 Jul 26 (Box 10, Folder 216)
        Includes photograph of Whitman's cabin in "Rock Creek Park"
  - WRITINGS
    - Writings of Walt Whitman
      - Memoranda During the War, frontispiece, page proof, [ca. 1875] (Box 10, Folder 217)
      - "Memories of Abraham Lincoln," setting copy (2 copies), n.d.
      - November Boughs, galley sheet, inscribed, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 218)
        Includes four poems
      - "Old Age's Ship & Crafty Death's," poem, galley proof, corrected, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 219)
      - "Sea-Captains, Young or Old," poem, holograph, corrected, [1875?] (Box 10, Folder 220)
      - "Shak[e]spe[a]re-Bacon's Cipher," poem, galley proof, inscribed, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 221)
      - ["Whitman, Walt, poet, was born..."], autobiographical statement, holograph, corrected, 1888 (Box 10, Folder 222)
    - Writings of Others
      - Miller, Edwin Haviland
        - "Walt Whitman as a Lobbyist," galley proof for The Yale University Library Gazette, 1960 Dec 23
          Includes note to Miller from Donald Gallup
      - Untermeyer, Louis
        - The Poetry and Prose of Walt Whitman, (volumes 1-2), galley proof, 1949 (Box 10, Folder 223-226)
  - PHOTOGRAPHS
    - Eakins, Thomas, 1887 Apr (Box 11, Folder 227)
    - G. F. E. Pearsall, 1872 Sep (Box 11, Folder 228)
    - [Kurtz, William?], [1892?] (Box 11, Folder 229)
    - Major & Knapp Engraving, Manufacturing & Lithographic Co., 1879 (Box 11, Folder 230)
    - Murray, Samuel, 1891 (Box 11, Folder 231)
    - Sarony & Co.
      See: Major & Knapp Engraving, Manufacturing & Lithographic Co., Box 11, folder 230
    - Unidentified, 1879, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 232)
  - ARTWORK
    - S.[amuel] Hollyer engravings, [1855] (Box 11, Folder 233)
    - T. Johnson etching, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 234)
    - G[ustav?] Kruell engraving, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 235)
    - W[illiam] J[ames] Linton engraving, 1878 (Box 11, Folder 236)
    - S[tephen] A[lonzo] Schoff engravings (2 copies), n.d. (Box Art, Folder 237)
    - C. P. Williams engraving, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 238)
    - Unidentified, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 239)
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - Clipping of letter from Whitman to Thomas Nicholson, Ladies Home Journal, 1923 Sep (Box 11, Folder 240)
    - Postcards, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 241)
    - Printed ephemera, 1886, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 242)
    - Whitman signature, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 243)
- Oversize, 6.84; (4 boxes)
  - Galley proofs for "Fifty-First New-York City Veterans" (In Series IV), 1864 Oct 29 (Box 12, Folder 244)
  - Galley proof for "The Soldiers, &c" (In Series IV), 1865 Feb (Box 13, Folder 245)
  - Papers concerning New York Civil War regiments (In Series IV), 1864-65, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 246)
  - Letter from Walt Whitman to William Michael Rossetti (In Series V), 1867 Dec 3 (Box 13, Folder 247)
  - Galley proof for "Death of Carlyle" (In Series V), [ca. 1881] (Box 13, Folder 248)
  - Galley proof for "An Old Man's Rejoinder" (In Series V) (Box 13, Folder 249)
  - Galley proof for "Old Poets" (In Series V) (Box 13, Folder 250)
  - Galley proof for "Preface" (In Series V) (Box 13, Folder 251)
  - Galley proof for "The Soldiers, &c" (In Series V), 1865 Feb (Box 13, Folder 252)
  - Holograph drafts and galley proof of "Fancies at Navesink" (In Series V) (Box 14, Folder 253)
  - Holograph manuscript of "Osceola" (In Series V), n.d. (Box 14, Folder 254)
  - Holograph drafts and printed version of "Song of the Universal" (In Series V), 1874, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 255)
  - Holograph manuscript of "A Voice From Death" (In Series V), n.d. (Box 14, Folder 256)
  - Galley proof for "Address at the Funeral of Walt Whitman" (In Series V), [1892] (Box 15, Folder 257)
  - George C. Cox photographs (In Series V) (Box 15, Folder 258)
  - Photographs of Whitman by unidentified photographers (In Series V), 1864, 1882 (Box 15, Folder 259)
  - John C. Hemment photographs (In Series V) (Box 15, Folder 260)
  - Bertrand Zadig woodcut (In Series V) (Box 15, Folder 261)
  - Setting copies for "Memories of Abraham Lincoln" (In Series VI), n.d. (Box 15, Folder 262)
  - Galley proof for Edwin Haviland Miller's "Walt Whitman as a Lobbyist" (In Series VI), 1960 Dec 23 (Box 15, Folder 263)
  - T. Johnson etching (In Series VI), n.d. (Box 15, Folder 264)
  - Printed advertisement (2 copies) (In Series VI), n.d. (Box 15, Folder 265)
- Restricted Fragile Papers, 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 1, folder 40 (Box 16, Folder 266)
  - Box 1, folder 57 (Box 16, Folder 267)
  - Box 1, folder 58 (Box 16, Folder 268)
  - Box 3, folder 140 (Box 16, Folder 269)
  - Box 4, folder 198 (Box 16, Folder 270)
  - Box 4, folder 199 (Box 17, Folder 271)
  - Box 4, folder 201 (Box 17, Folder 272)